On Treatment
After consultation, plan approval, and completion
of planning steps, your treatment begins.
You will return to the department for treatment during
your personalized treatment plan’s dates and times.
Frequency and number of treatments varies
from patient to patient.
You may come back daily, every other day,
or be done with treatment all together.
How long each treatment session takes can
vary depending on your particular situation,
but on average they last around 20 minutes and
entail two steps: set-up and delivery of radiation.
For set-up, you will be placed in the same
position as your CT simulation scan
and a cone-beam CT will be performed to
ensure proper placement.
After being placed in the correct position
and the position is verified,
external beam radiation to the target area begins.
Once a week,
while you are receiving treatment,
you will see your doctor in the clinic
who will check in with you
during this on treatment visit or OTV.
This is a great time to discuss
any side effects or other symptoms
you may be feeling, and dive
into what treatments are available.
Additionally,
you may meet with our registered dietitian
to discuss your weight
and nutritional status.
There are also many other support staff
available to you.
Should you require their services,
such as our social worker
and many skilled registered nurses.
While we are scheduled to see you
once a week at minimum.
If you have any of the following
or any urgent concerns
in between OTVs
please do not hesitate to contact us.
A temperature of
104°F 38°C or higher.
Chills.
Increasing pain or discomfort.
Increased redness or swelling
or skin that is hard or hot to the touch.
A rash or blistering of your skin
in the treated area.
Drainage
from your skin in the treated area.
Any new open areas
or changes to your skin.